all right so why should you listen to
some guy standing in front of a
whiteboard with a white T-shirt on my
name is Matt I'm a current strategy and
operations associate at Google prior to
that was a Management Consultant at BCG
and today I'm going to walk you through
yet another McKenzie style case the
reason why I'm making this video is
because I've made similar walkthroughs
in the past and you guys have really
liked it and so without further Ado
let's get right into it all right so the
case we're going to do today is called
deona so the buillt in Melinda Gates
Foundation is a private organization
with vast Ambitions one of its goals is
to reduce extreme poverty worldwide the
foundation has asked Mackenzie to design
a basic Financial Services offering for
residents in remote communities in
Mexico the majority of Mexico's rural
population is relatively poor relying in
part on government benefits for their
livelihood since they do not have bank
accounts they usually collect those
benefits in cash from a limited number
of state-owned Bank branches these
branches are often a long way from where
the recipients live so it can take a lot
of time and effort to collect benefits
in addition while traveling to the
branches people can be at risk of
falling victim to Crime so the Mexican
Government also owns and operates a
chain of 22,000 stores throughout Mexico
called deona which provide basic food
clothes and other essential Goods to
rural populations these stores are
supplied through a network of Central
and Regional warehouses and several
thousand delivery trucks and so McKenzie
has been asked to investigate and assess
the possibility of using the Duna
Network to provide a set of basic
Financial Services to supplement The
Limited number of state-owned Bank
branches this would start with
dispensing benefit payments and would
gradually grow to include savings
accounts bill payments insurance loans
and other Financial products so the
first thing we always want to do when we
are starting a case and we're hearing
the prompt is we want to be taking notes
and so obviously I wasn't taking notes
while I was reading it but I'm going to
write a few things down right now okay
so I just wrote down a few quick notes
right here and so I've written down that
we have Deans which is a set of 22,000
stores throughout Mexico there's a
Mexican government program that looks to
fund rural communities throughout Mexico
and so the question at hand today is
should we distribute the funds and other
Financial products
via this network of 22,000 stores versus
what we've been just doing which has
just been distribution through
state-owned banks where the distribution
might not be as efficient or easy for
the recipients to access and so what I'm
going to do next is I'm going to
brainstorm just a few clarifying
questions and the reason why you always
want to brainstorm at least two or three
clarifying questions after hearing the
prompt is you want to demonstrate to the
interviewer that you're paying attention
and also it can help you to potentially
identify New pieces of information that
might be useful for you if anything it
just helps to deepen your understanding
of the context and it never hurts to
show the interviewer that you're
thinking thoughtfully about the prompt
all right so what I've done right here
is I've just quickly drafted out three
clarifying questions that you could
potentially ask now I want to caveat
that you do not have to ask the
questions that I came up with these are
simply the ones that came to mind for me
but as long as you just think about two
or three clarifying questions I think
this works just fine and so I'll walk
you through what I've brainstormed here
so the first clarifying question is how
will fun funds actually be distributed
in the program and the reason why I
asked this is because right now I also
want to understand is the fund flow
process still going to be government
Bank to State Bank to deona or is it
going to go straight from government to
deona and the reason why I'm curious
about that is because I'm thinking about
the time that it's going to take to
distribute funds to the stores and I'm
thinking about the efficiency and how
many steps it's going to take now I
don't know a ton about how the Mexican
Financial system works and so this would
be an area to understand a little bit
deeper but potentially my interviewer
might tell me that oh so right now we
have a government Central Bank that
distributes to State Banks and if we
were to use the deona program we would
still distribute to State Banks and then
have them distribute to deona and so
that would give me a little bit of a
better understanding of what we're
working with and that okay we are going
to still have to have two steps to this
process but anyway the second question
that I asked was do we have majority
support and I'm talking about support
within the Mexican Government because
again like any sort of initiative or new
bill or legislature assuming of course
we're talking about a democratic country
we are going to need at least majority
support in the political system in order
to get this program even approved and so
this is an important question to ask now
the third question that I want to ask is
how secure are the deona stores and this
is important because again we're dealing
with money here and so obviously Bank
security is really really high but once
you start Distributing Financial
products and cash to basically
convenience stores then the likelihood
that one these stores could get robbed
or two the recipients could get their
funds and then get robbed pretty quickly
after that is quite high in my mind and
so I really want to understand how
secure these stores are or whether or
not there are some sort of security
measures that are planned to account for
the risk of theft all right but
basically after you ask your clarifying
questions the interviewer will give you
some feedback related to those questions
and and so oftentimes they will either
tell you that no we don't have any
information on this yet but this is why
we've hired you or they'll give you some
pieces of additional detail additional
information that might help you to think
a little bit deeper about the prompt but
after you do that what you want to do
immediately after is you want to move
into developing your framework and so
the way you do this is you ask the
interviewer for some time in order to
develop it and so I would say okay great
this sounds really interesting to me can
I take a minute or two to structure my
thoughts and they will always say yes
and this is your cue to go ahead and
think through putting together a
framework and for those of you who don't
know what a framework is a framework is
just a fancy word for a set of key
buckets that you would explore in order
to better understand a problem or
situation and it's a very important part
of structured thinking which is
something that you're being tested on in
case interviews and so I'm going to put
together a quick framework right now all
right so what I've done right here is
I've just put together a quick framework
and just before I walk you through it I
do want to say today what I've done is I
have used a value chain framework and
this simply means it's a framework where
you look at every single person or
entity involved in the quote unquote
value chain and you look at all the
considerations that each party has to
think about related to this program and
so I've listed out four buckets here
with each of the four main key players
in the value chain and so the first one
is the Mexican Government the second is
the state- known Banks the third is the
deona network stores themselves and then
the fourth is the recipients the
families that are actually receiving
this Aid and so basically the way you
want to walk your interviewer through
the framework is you always want to
start by saying okay great so I've taken
some time to think through a framework
and broadly speaking there are four
buckets that I would want to explore to
get a better understanding of the
situation and think through a
recommendation and so the first is going
to be related to The Mexican government
the second the state own Banks the third
the deona network stores and then the
fourth the actual recipients of the aid
and within each bucket I've thought
through some benefits and considerations
related to each party so that we can
think holistically about the pros and
cons of this program but now to walk you
through the first bucket which is the
Mexican Government here on the benefit
side what I can see as the immediate
benefits for the Mexican Government to
implement this program are one if the
program is successful and say they are
able to actually speed up the process of
getting Aid to these families and the
families like it then they're going to
get a lot of positive PR and positive
support at least from that population
and so for example the policy makers
that might be backing this initiative
would want to see that happen similarly
You could argue that there is some sort
of economic impact here because I would
imagine that say for example if I am
someone who walks into a deona store and
I'm going there to get one thing which
is my funds I might also pick up some
other Goods while I'm there right I
don't know about you guys but for me
whenever I say that I'm going to get
milk at the grocery store I almost
always end up walking out with two or
three other things and so there is some
impact I don't know how big it is but
potentially we could estimate an
economic impact to the Mexican economy
driven by higher foot traffic to these
stores but let's switch to the
considerations and on the consideration
side I would say that political
opposition is going to be a big
potential risk to this program even
getting through in the first place
because not everybody May support this
program but assuming we even do get this
approved there was a significant amount
of execution risk as well execution risk
simply being like how do we actually get
it done right someone is going to have
to think about okay which stores do we
want to involve in this program maybe we
want to start out with some sort of
pilot where we only use a small set of
stores first to test out whether this is
going to be successful before we roll it
out to all 22,000 and even within that
pilot how do we actually initiate it how
do we handle the logistics of even
sending the money to these stores is the
Mexican Government going to handle this
is the state-owned banks going to handle
it how do we manage the security
concerns around it there's a whole set
of execution risks involved with
successfully handling this program but
moving to the second bucket which is our
state loan Banks here on the benefit
side I would say the state loan Banks
probably don't have as many benefits to
gain from the fact that we're now going
to distribute funds through this network
of stores as opposed to only their Banks
but you could say higher efficiency and
more predictability around their funds
flowing out of the bank is going to be a
benefit because now if you know for
example that every month you're going to
have to send 100,000 pesos to a network
of 22,000 stores then you're going to be
able to factor in that outflow of funds
in a very predictable manner versus how
it used to be in the past where maybe
100,000 people would come to your Banks
but that amount would fluctuate each
month maybe some months certain people
didn't come in other months more people
than you expected came in and so it was
a little bit difficult to predict how
much funds you needed and so that's
going to be the most immediate benefit
in my mind to the state Lo Banks but on
the consideration side they're obviously
going to now get less foot traffic and
so less foot traffic could potentially
mean less business right because now
instead of 10,000 people coming into
your bank every year maybe it's going to
be cut in half and you'll only have
5,000 people coming into the bank and so
these are potential customers that could
have maybe signed up for some other
products at your bank there was a detail
in the prompt that mentioned the
eventual plan for the Decon Network
would be to move to other Financial
products not just cash payments and so
there is potentially still a benefit
here for the state owned Banks but still
something to consider and also less
Capital to potentially use for other
things Banks make money based off of the
fact that they take one person's
deposits and then they use those funds
to lend to other people and then earn
interest on those loans and so if for
example we are sending a significant
amount amount of money out to these
stores then the bank itself is going to
have less money to hold on to to
potentially invest in other things but
now if we move to the third bucket which
is the deona network here I would say
the benefits are going to be the fact
that these stores are now going to get
much more foot traffic with people
coming in to get their deposits or maybe
sign up for other Financial products and
in addition to that they'll probably
also pick up other Goods again whenever
I say I'm going to go to the store to
buy milk or eggs I always end up coming
out with at least a bag full of things
and so for the stores at least there is
probably going to be some sort of uplift
in their sales because people are going
to just be buying more things assuming
that your conversion rate aka the
percentage of people that come into your
store that actually buy something stays
the same then if your foot traffic
increases then your revenue is going to
increase but then of course we have to
talk about the considerations and here's
where I think it gets interesting
because the number one thing we have to
remember is this is money here that
we're transporting and going to be
storing at basically a convenience store
and when people find out that there is
going to be a lot more money being
stored within the DCA stores than there
is going to be obviously a higher risk
of crime and so I think the biggest
consideration here is going to be
security related and how specifically
are we going to mitigate the risk that
criminals will come in Rob the store
break into the safe and steal a bunch of
money finally to round it out with the
recipients of the aid themselves Mexican
families what are they going to benefit
from theoretically convenience because
they're going to be able to get their
funds quicker they don't have to travel
as far and therefore they also save on
Transportation costs and so it would be
convenience plus I'll put dollar sign
for money because you're supposed to
save money in practice I don't know if
that's actually what's going to happen
but on the consideration side again
security is going to be the biggest one
because again if I walk out of the
grocery store with like $5,000 in cash
in my back pocket and the grocery store
is in a kind of shady area then there's
a high risk that I'm going to get mucked
and so how are we actually going to
mitigate that and then secondarily I've
written down is it actually better now
in theory it's going to be quicker right
and it's going to be more convenient but
I would argue we have to think about is
this actually going to be more
beneficial because speed is one thing
but when we're talking about financial
products a lot of people don't
understand Financial products very well
and so customer support I would argue is
actually pretty important right and
there are a lot of people out there who
won't open up a new bank account or a
new checking or or credit card without
actually talking to like an agent at the
bank and so the stores are not going to
have that same level of customer support
and who's going to feel the pain of that
lack of customer support well it's going
to be the recipients okay so that was
the framework and so basically after you
walk your interviewer through the
framework you want to invite them to
give you some feedback and so you want
to say something along the lines of blah
blah blah and so these are the four
buckets that I would want to consider
but would love to hear your thoughts as
well I have a few ideas in mind of where
I think would be interesting to explore
but just want to get your thoughts as
well and so this is a way that you can
ask them subtly for feedback and maybe
they'll tell you that oh this sounds
really great let's Dive Right In or
they'll give you a little bit more
detail about one particular bucket but
in this case because this is a Mackenzie
style case it is interviewer Le which
means that the interviewer will guide
you to the next question which is the
team has estimated that it currently
costs a family 50 pesos per month in
transportation and food to make the
journey to collect benefit payments the
team also estimates that if benefits
were available for collection at local
deona stores the cost could be reduced
by 30% 20% of Mexican's population is
rural and of that number half currently
receives state benefits you can assume
that Mexico has a population of 100
million you can also assume that
families in Mexico have an average of
four members and that this does not vary
by region so if every family could
collect state benefits at their local
deona stores how much in total per year
would be saved across all Mexican Ral
families receiving state benefits okay
so basically this next question is a
quantitative portion of the case and
this is quite normal usually the second
part of the case interview is
quantitative in nature and so they've
given us a bunch of information here
which I will now write down really
quickly all right so what I've done here
is I've literally just listed out the
details that we were given for this
Quant portion we know that the cost per
family is 50 p a month to get the funds
and there's a projected 30% cost
reduction if we do begin using the deona
network to distribute this Aid the
Mexican population we've been given some
demographic info we know is 100 million
people there's roughly four people per
family on average and we know that of
this entire population 20% lives in
rural locations of which half AKA 10%
are currently receiving aid and so the
question at hand that we're trying to
answer is how much can we actually save
what would be the actual quantitative
impact of this network and so basically
to walk you through the logic of how I'm
going to do this I'm going to start by
calculating the status quo cost so what
does it cost people right now and then
I'm going to apply a 30% haircut or
discount to that cost number to get us
to our cost savings okay and so the
structure of the math would be as
follows we would start with our total
population and then we would divide by
the number of people per family to
basically get us to how many families
are in all of Mexico then we would
multiply it by the 20% of families that
currently live in rural areas and then
split that in half basically multiplying
by 50% to get to the amount that are
currently receiving aid so that's our
relevant number of families and then
we're just going to multiply by how much
it costs them so 50 pesos per month
times 12 pesos a year to get to our
status quo total cost number so I'm
going to do the math really quickly we
have 100 million families we divide by
four people per family which is about 25
million families take 20% of that AKA
divided by 5 so that's 5 million
families that are living in rural places
take half of that that are receiving aid
so 2.5 million families that are
actually receiving aid and then 50 pesos
time 12 months per year that's 600 pesos
a year which means that right now cost
them roughly 1.5 billion pesos per year
pretty small down there but this is just
the total cost and what we're trying to
get to is how much we can actually save
and we've been given that there's a
estimated 30% cost reduction if we use
the deona network so what is 30% of 1.5
billion well 30% of 1.5 billion is the
same as basically 3 * 150 million which
is the same as
450 million pesos so that's our final
number which is that if we use the deona
network we could hypothetically save 450
million pesos per year for these
families and so after you get to this
number you should stop and take a step
back and think about what this number
even means in the context of the case
and sometimes your interviewer will
press you to think about what this
number even means and so they might ask
you something like okay great so how
does this number make you feel and
sometimes it's not that they're looking
for a yes or no answer it's simply that
they want to understand that you know
that okay a number like 450 million is
really large but without any context or
anything to compare it to it doesn't
really have as much meaning as it could
if you had for example another number to
Benchmark it off of but as always make
sure to walk the interviewer through
your entire thought process think aloud
and do what I did and talk through the
structure of the math first before you
actually do it that way they can
potentially correct you or give you
guidance if you are a little bit lost
and once you've done all your math
immediately go into thinking about okay
what does this actually mean in the
context of the case but anyway this
brings us to the third question which is
that the team conducted a survey on a
sample of the rural population in three
different regions in Mexico participants
were shown several statements about the
concept of collecting benefits at their
nearest deona store and asked how much
they agreed with each statement the
average response to some of the
questions in each region is shown below
and so they've given us this exhibit
which basically shows us the results of
a rural population survey and whenever
you are given a exhibit in a case what
you always want to do is you want to
talk aloud and just give your initial
observation because not only does this
show the interviewer what you're
thinking but it also buys you time to
actually think through what the results
even mean because some times when you're
given a bunch of information or data you
might not have any sort of insight to
explain to the interviewer immediately
and so this allows you to show them your
thought process but also to digest the
information a little bit slowly so that
you can come up with some key insights
and so basically the question that the
interviewer will posos to you is what
are your observations regarding this
information and how would you explain
these Trends and so this section of the
case is going to be a little bit more
conversational just because they're
giving you an exhibit and they're
basically just asking you to explain the
trends and so I want to caveat that
there's really no right or wrong answer
in this situation but there are better
answers and there are worse answers and
so as long as you have a rationale
behind why the results turned out a
certain way and you can back it up
logically and with sound reasoning then
you should be okay here and so basically
there were six dimensions that were
tested in this survey one was are you
happy to receive your benefits another
was how secure do you feel receiving
your benefits and then there was trust
so do I trust that I will receive my
benefits do I think that the cost will
be lower because of this program and do
I think that it'll be faster as well so
the way I would walk through this with
my interviewer is again I would say okay
so it looks like across the board
Everyone likes speed and thinks that
speed is going to be a big benefit of
this program but that said it looks like
there are some significant differences
when it comes to something like security
because region B seems to rate much
lower than regions A and C when it comes
to believing that they will feel secure
about receiving their payments and so
this leads me to believe that there's
something about region B that makes
people feel not safe so maybe it's more
crime or perhaps the deona stores are
located in areas that are a little bit
more dangerous and so people don't
necessarily feel more secure even though
they believe that of course it's
convenient like yes it's down the street
but also I might get mugged now what
does this mean for us well maybe it
means that if we are to rule this out
then we need to implement additional
security measures here
right so you want to extrapolate Beyond
just the first order insight and you
want to go beyond to a second or third
level so you want to say yes I've
observed this and I think that it is
because of this but that leads me to
believe that maybe a way to mitigate it
would be to do this so you go multiple
layers deep to demonstrate to the
interviewer that you are not just
looking at the data and understanding it
but you're also thinking about okay what
does this actually mean and what can we
actually recommend to the client to
either mitigate this or improve the
situation and so similarly to security
trust is also the lowest in region and
so I think this we can also assume is
due to the fact that they're probably in
a higher crime region and so they just
don't believe as confidently that they
will actually receive their benefits
which is valid but what is also
interesting is they actually have the
lowest in terms of cost as well when it
comes to the regions which indicates
something interesting to me because of
course security and Trust are sort of
related so I can understand that if this
is a high crime area they will have the
least amount of security and Trust in
the program but how does that translate
into the fact that people in Regent B
felt that they did not believe it would
cost less to receive their benefits well
I think there's multiple factors here
that could contribute to that one could
be just overall perception in that they
could be factoring in oh I might get
robbed as a potential cost but another
possibility could be that maybe region B
just happens to have less deona stores
in general or maybe the deona stores are
actually further from some of these
recipients than say their state-owned
bank branch and so counterintuitively it
might actually cost them more to go to
the store than to actually go to the
local bank but anyways I've just
brainstormed a few reasons here why
these results might be the case in an
actual case scenario you want to just
come up with as many reasons as you
possibly can and have a thorough
discussion with your interviewer it is
again less about getting the right
answer and more about whether or not you
can actually back up your answer with
sound rationale and logic behind why you
think something is the case because at
the end of the day in Consulting you
want to be hypothesis driven and so you
always want to go into a situation with
basically a problem statement that you
want to either prove or disprove and it
is totally okay if your hypothesis gets
disproved Based on data that you find I
think what's most important here is just
to be presentable and to demonstrate to
your interviewer that you can think
logically and have a bit of business
sense when it comes to thinking about
different options and What might explain
the results but anyway that brings us to
the fourth question which is in a
subsequent meeting representatives from
the state-owned bank Express concern
about how challenging it will be to
offer basic Financial products to the
rural population one of the
representatives mentions that these are
regions where people have minimal
education and are unfamiliar with
banking products there is also a
significant crime and fraud he asks for
the team's thoughts about how the bank
could sell these Services effectively to
the population given these challenges
okay so this is again another
brainstorming section basically you're
just going to try to come up with as
many ideas as possible for how you can
basically educate your consumers on
these Financial products and so I just
also want to say before any sort of
brainstorming section feel free to ask
your interviewer for like 30 seconds to
come up with a few ideas if you don't
have any that immediately come to mind I
think it's always better to ask for a
bit of time and have more thought out
answers than to just dive into something
that you're not totally prepared to talk
about because that's always just a bad
look and so I'm just going to take a few
seconds right now to write down a few
ideas all right so I've just thrown
together a few quick ideas here for how
we can better educate the population on
these Financial products and overall
just increase their familiarity with
what we are offering and so the first
bucket is just what I call inore events
and so this is super easy for the stores
to do they can basically go ahead and
plan out maybe once a week or once a
month or once every couple months an
event that they can throw in the store
where there are different activities but
also the main goal of the event is to of
course educate the customers that come
through about what the new products are
what they offer and how you can sign up
for them and so I think the store
managers themselves can decide how they
want to run these but if the government
wants they can also chip in and provide
funding or assistance with planning and
running these events the second thing is
you want to educate your employees
because if you're employees don't know
how these products even work then
there's very low likelihood that they're
going to promote these to the customers
and so if you can first maybe set up
seminars or webinars to educate the
employees at the stores of what the
offerings are how they should be
teaching people about them and just get
them familiar first then it'll be easier
to implement some sort of incentive
programs for your employees to say
introduce more customers to the
different banking products offered
through this program but finally we also
have Partnerships and other promotions
and this will be things like partnering
with another company in the region that
is very popular another brand that
people are familiar with some sort of
household name and running a promotion
where for example maybe someone who gets
into your store maybe if they buy bread
from a brand that they really like they
also happen to get a discount on opening
up a bank account or a new checking
account on the reverse side you could
also do something similar where you
basically say hey if you open up a new
checking or savings account then you can
get a 5% off on your next purchase with
this particular brand that you really
really like but finally this brings us
to the end of the case which is going to
involve your recommendation and
synthesis and I always tell people to
take a few seconds to come up with the
recommendation instead of just jumping
right into it the typical way that the
question is posed by the interviewer
will be that hey so and so say Bill
Gates or The Mexican government is
walking down the hall and they're about
to come into the conference room where
you and your team have been working for
the past couple days and ask for a
status update what would you tell them
about what you've learned and so the
structure that I always recommend people
follow is one you start with restating
the context two you give your
recommendation three you talk about
risks and then four you talk about next
steps and what you always want to do
before you actually give the
recommendation is you want to look back
on your paper and you want to think
about all of the things that you've
learned today all the different insights
any numbers anything that you've learned
that might be informative to the
recommendation because you want to use
them in your explanation and so the way
I would give the recommendation is I
would say awesome thanks so much for
joining us today as you know we've been
working really hard to think about the
considerations related to launching the
deona Network to support this aid
program for families in Mexico and after
all of our research we would recommend
going through with utilizing the deona
network to distribute the funds to
families throughout Mexico we think that
there's a lot of benefit to this in fact
through our analysis we've actually
found that there is going to be a
roughly 450 million peso savings impact
that we think can be reasonably achieved
as long as we have a solid execution
plan in place now that said there are
obviously a number of considerations
most notably being the fact that there
are a lot of concerns around security
and Trust and safety which is what we
found based on our consumer survey and
so we would recommend as a next step
further looking into how we might want
to increase the security around the
deona network and really make our
customers feel safe receiving their aid
at these stores instead of a state run
bank and we think a big part of this is
also going to be education and so we'd
also recommend looking into educational
initiatives to just increase overall
awareness about our different Financial
products going forward but anyways that
was the case and if you are currently
struggling on case interviewing or you
think you would benefit from a little
bit of assistance I do also offer
one-on-one coaching where I can better
tailor my advice towards your situation
and help you really improve your casing
abilities if that sounds interesting to
you then check out the link in my
description below but with that thanks
again for stopping by and I'll see you
guys in the next one peace